<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian meditacion or praier to be sayed at all tymes whensoeuer God shall vyset vs wyth anye mortall plague or sicnesse</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1551</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S113545</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848778</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848778</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13892</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13892)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 736:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian meditacion or praier to be sayed at all tymes whensoeuer God shall vyset vs wyth anye mortall plague or sicnesse</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By [S. Mierdman for] Wylliam Awen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1551.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13892:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13892:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian meditacion or prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to be ſayed at all ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes whenſoeuer GOD ſhall vyſet vs wyth anye mortall plague or ſic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprynted at Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don By Wylliam Awen 1.5.5.1.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:13892:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Chriſtian meditacyon or prayer to meditacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or prayer to be ſaid at all tymes when ſoeuer God ſhal viſet vs with any mortal plage or ſicknes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord GOD almighty and Father moſte merciful, who thoughe thou be dayly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked to wrathe and venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce by the grieuous offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and ſinnes of vs thy moſt diſobedient children, yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe art ſo pacient and of ſuch long ſufferaunce, that thou holdeſte thy rod, tyll by our outrageous contemptes and moſt wilfull breakinges of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes thou
<pb facs="tcp:13892:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>art for our correccion co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtreig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to ſtrike: remember good Lord thine accuſtomed good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe towardes thy people, whome of thine owne father<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thenderneſſe thou hadeſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer more lieffer to ſaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſpill, to emend the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to deſtroy, to forgeue then to punyſhe. What ſoeuer ſcourge or afflie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions thou diddeſt in old time eyther threaten or laye vpon the ſtubberne &amp; vnrepentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce people of Iſraell, yet dyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt thou neuer ſhutte vp thy mercies from them whan ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer they woulde wyth all their herte returne vnto the.<note place="margin">Gene. 18.</note> Whan the crye of Zodome &amp; Gomorre came vnto thyne eare for their moſt grieuous abominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: yet ſuch is thy readines to ſhew mercy, that
<pb facs="tcp:13892:3"/>at the prayer of thy ſeruaunt Abraham thou madeſte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to ſaue the cityes and not to deſtroy them. Firſte if fifty, ſecondely if fourtye fiue, than yf fortye, afterwarde if thirty,<note place="margin">Ioan. 3.</note> at laſt if twenty, yea fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nally if tenne righteous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones could haue bene found in them. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy Prophete Ionas had proclaimed the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtruccion of Niniue for their great and manifolde ſinnes: yet for their repentaunce ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke, thou diddeſt moſt gladly and readily call backe thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſentence afore pronounced againſt them.<note place="margin">4. Re. 20</note> Whan thy Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete Iſay had at thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demente declared to Kynge Ezechias that he ſhoulde not ſcape death, yet for his herty prayers ſake thou diddeſt re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoke
<pb facs="tcp:13892:3"/>that ſentence agayne, &amp; diddeſt adde, fyfteen yeares vnto his dayes. And we alſo now O Lorde acknowledge our manifold ſinnes and moſt grieuous tranſgreſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. We confeſſe that we haue moſte iuſtely deſerued this ſodayn plague &amp; mortall diſeaſe and a greate deale wurſe. We graunt that we haue by oure wickedneſſe, moſte worthely enke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dled thy wrathe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignacion againſt vs. But o Lord what is man that thou wouldeſt matche thy ſelfe to trye in battaill agaynſt him: What glory ſhould it be, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> o Lorde, if thou ſhouldeſte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all fleaſh beyng but chaf and duſte. Remember good Lord that yf thou wilt ſtand in triall with vs, we haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge
<pb facs="tcp:13892:4"/>to lay for our ſelfes, nor can be hable to ſtande in iudgemente before the. We therfore appeale from thy iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice vnto thy mercy, whyche for thy names ſake &amp; for thine owne glory, thou haſt in thine eternall woorde and trueth promyſed vnto all ſuche as will earneſtly emend and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uert vnto the. Spar vs the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refore good Lorde, and like as thou haſt at this preſente ſent vnto vs this ſodayn pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue both as a warning of thy greate indignacion for oure moſt grieuous ſinnes, and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo for a token that except we will now emende, we cannot eſcape thy handes to be bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with a ſharper rodde: ſo graunte O Lorde that thys maye be vnto vs an holſome
<pb facs="tcp:13892:4"/>medicyne for oure emende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of lyfe, and that it may all together redounde vnto thy glorye, ſo that whether we lyue or dye we maye ſtyll bee thy people, and thou ſtill our God and moſt tendre lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father. And foraſmuch as euerye good gyfte of true fayth &amp; repentaunce cometh from the geue vs thy grate that we may by this thy moſt tendre and fatherly correcci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, returne from our did ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities whych haue now pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uoked thy wrathe, and alſo that from henſforth we may ſerue the in all holineſſe and pureneſſe of lyfe, wherby thy glorye may encreaſe, and thy name may be magnified. Yea euen emong them that other wiſe are blaſphemers of thy
<pb facs="tcp:13892:5"/>moſt holy Ghoſpell, and doe impute vnto the knowledge of thy moſt holy woorde ſent vnto the world in theſe later times, al the plagues. Which haue bene prouoked by oure ſtubberneſſe and hardeneſſe of herte. But heare thou O Lorde the hertye prayers of the faithfull litell flocke tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyng in thy only mercy: and graunte thys oure petycyon for thy Sonne IESVS Chriſtes ſake, to whom with the, and thee Holye Ghooſte bee all prayſe, honoure and glorye for euer and euer. Soo bee it.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
